# Sam Younan

# **Director of Corporate Software Development - Sabre Systems Inc**

Burlington, NJ - Email me on Indeed: indeed.com/r/Sam-Younan/50c7bcdcae2db5db

Highly professional, foresighted and analytical IT professional with extensive experience delivering costeffective software solutions & serving hundreds of employees and customers. Demonstrated strengths in corporate engineering, technology implementation, development and management of diverse technical teams. Recognized for exhibiting excellence in performance, productivity, and growth strategies. Experienced in the pharmaceuticals, financial, and government contracts industries. Open & willing to relocate in the US and internationally to select locations.

- Executing project on client & business process needs and developing a roadmap for the evolution of the IT Architecture through planning and integration of legacy environments into a transformed environment.
- Competencies entail participation in and management of application development projects in enterprise and Financial Solutions.
- Verifiable experience in Project Management Life Cycle including project planning, scheduling & negotiations with the client for service level agreements / terms, project progress monitoring and delivery as per quality and time terms.
- Demonstrated skills in managing on-site team members throughout the project Lifecycle while maintaining coordination with stakeholders and providing them regular updates about the project.
- Experience in IT strategy planning, budgeting, and implementation, as well as web development, object-oriented analysis and design, relational databases, SharePoint architecture/administration and client server applications.
- Analyst, with a flair for adapting quickly to dynamic business environments and adopting a pragmatic approach in improvising on solutions and resolving complex business issues.

Profit Driven Analysis & Strategic Measures Project Management & Sustainable Solutions

Acknowledged for capacity to analyze issues, expedite innovative solutions, and build the type of consensusdriven environment that contributes to on time, on-budget delivery.

Recognized for ability to establish, target, and meet all facets of the project Lifecycle to achieve critical goals & provide competitive IT Solutions.

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

### **Director of Corporate Software Development**

Sabre Systems Inc - Warrington, PA - 2005 to Present

Lead IT projects and involved in accomplishing project deadlines. Directed and steered functions like defining scope, assigning priorities, delegating responsibilities and managing recruitments. Highly instrumental in the delivery of cost-saving, firm-wide payroll software to a commercial client, building an interactive website for another client, and the introduction of the EPM Live Work Engine to streamline in-house project management.

- Effectively leading a team of application engineers with variety and in depth scope of responsibilities such as Analysis, design, implementation, and testing functional/upcoming applications, daily management of support resources, migrating applications, performing training (on-site/off-site) operations, participate and contribute during development meetings with clients (internal/external), monitoring smooth functioning of production environments and collaborating with Project Engineering Team and Architecture team.

- Engaged in definition, design, development and maintenance of specific MIS, including production and maintenance of associated documentation. Rendered operational support for the creation of relevant data files, databases, reports, prints etc. in daily operations.
- Scope of responsibilities expands to render constant technical support for applications to ensure optimal durability and reliability Investigated and resolved technical operational issues of the applications and involved in training end-users by means of verbal personal instruction and specially designed documentation.
- Played a key role in framing project plans, managing cost, scheduling, and performance, producing project status reports, monitoring project activities, and establishing rapport and maintaining communication with stakeholders at multiple levels.
- Conceptualized, designed, proposed and managed a project management software solution from EPM Live that changed the entire company's project portfolio management (PPM) and is being utilized by all project managers.
- Highly instrumental in improving interdepartmental coordination and reducing administration costs by 30% through the implementation of the SharePoint 2010 User Profile and My Site features. Configured and managed the implementation of SharePoint 2010 Form-based Authentication for Extranet sites utilizing an FBA suite for user management.
- Upgraded SharePoint with latest versions to allow the use of InfoPath forms automations and other business intelligence capabilities.

# IT Project Manager - Senior Consultant

Sabre Systems Inc - Warrington, PA - 2001 to 2005

Instrumental in planning and executing innovative strategies to achieve objectives for infrastructure improvement; redefined the scope of the project and coordinated resources. Built and managed successful client relationships ensuring all business needs were met.

- A key player in the development of strategies for several in-house systems; including assisting with validation and data collection on all systems and development of test strategies for transitioned applications.
- Achieved all project objectives within a short period of time; defined Statement of Work for the project, identified server and application, created a copy of server and application, and coordinated to execute a Statement of Work.

Highlights during the tenure include -

- Creation of the Radio Sawa website, www.radiosawa.com.
- Configuration of SharePoint Sites for numerous government clients including, the Drug Enforcement Administration, Naval Sea Systems Command 04, Expeditionary Airfields, Census Bureau, TACAMO, and PMA 261.
- Prepared, installed, configured, and upgraded finance software suite: Deltek CostPoint, Deltek e-Timesheet,
  Deltek CostPoint CRM, and Deltek Enterprise Planner applications.
- Implemented Primavera Project Management Product Suite which includes application server, SQL database server, and Primavera client server.
- Successful deployment of SharePoint Team Services of Cherry Hill Public School System and Adolor Corporation.
- Effectively utilized Visual Basic, XML and MS Exchange development to design and implement a commuter matching system for the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority.
- Designed and developed the company intranet http://www.mysabre.com using classic ASP with Microsoft SQL2000 database.

#### **Senior Software Developer**

Advanta Business Services - Voorhees, NJ - 1997 to 2000

## **Research Analyst**

Bristol-Myers Squibb - New Brunswick, NJ - 1995 to 1996

**EDUCATION** 

**PMTI** Institute

2011

College of Southern Maryland - Lexington Park, MD 2010

# **Master of Computer Science in Computer Science**

New Jersey Institute of Technology - Newark, NJ 2000

# **Bachelor of Science in Chemistry**

Jersey City University - Jersey City, NJ 1995

Princeton - Princeton, NJ

#### **CERTIFICATIONS**

# **PMP - Project Management Professional**

## **MCPS: Microsoft Certified Professional**

#### **ITIL Foundation**

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

TECHNICAL SKILL SET

#### Languages

- ASP Dot Net / C / C++ / C#
- JavaScript / VB Script
- ASP / XML / HTML / DHTML

### Relational Databases

- MS SQL Server 2000/ 2005, 2008, 2014
- MS Access [...] 2013
- SQL\*PLUS

## Applications and Tools

- Microsoft Office 365
- Windows Azure
- Share Point Portal 2003, 2007, 2010, 2013
- SharePoint Designer 2007, 2010, 2013
- Microsoft InfoPath 2007, 2010, 2013
- Microsoft Project 2010, 2013
- Deltek Product Suite
- SharePoint Control Point

• FBA Suite for SharePoint 2010

# Operating Systems:

- MS Windows Server 2003, 2008, 2012
- MS DOS/ MS Windows XP / Vista, 7
- Linux Ubuntu

# Hardware/Virtualization

- MVware, Open Box
- Dell Servers / Workstations
- HP Servers